<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The lay-Christian's obligation to read the Holy Scriptures</title>
            <author>Stratford, Nicholas, 1633-1707.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1687</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 78 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A61806</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S5934</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R20560</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11774385</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11774385</idno>
            <idno type="VID">48914</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A61806)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 48914)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 550:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The lay-Christian's obligation to read the Holy Scriptures</title>
                  <author>Stratford, Nicholas, 1633-1707.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 38 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Richard Chiswell ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1687.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Nicholas Stratford. cf. DNB.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible --  Study and teaching --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:48914:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:48914:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE <hi>Lay-Chriſtian's</hi> OBLIGATION To Read The Holy Scriptures.</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="lat" type="imprimatur">
               <body>
                  <p>Imprimatur.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>H. Maurice R<hi rend="sup">mo.</hi> P. D. Wilhelmo Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiep. Cant. à Sacris.</signed>
                     <date>Decemb. 10. 1686. </date>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Richard Chiſwell,</hi> at the <hi>Roſe</hi> and <hi>Crown</hi> in S. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-Yard.</p>
            <p>MDCLXXXVII.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:48914:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:48914:2"/>
            <head>COLOSS. III. 16. <hi>Let the word of Chriſt dwell in you richly, in all Wiſdom.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>WHich words are an intire Precept of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; thoſe which follow in the ſame Verſe, <hi>(teaching and admoniſhing,</hi> &amp;c.) being another diſtinct from it.</p>
            <p>As preparatory to that which I intend from them, I ſhall premiſe theſe two things: Firſt, To whom this Precept is addreſs'd. Secondly, What is the import of the Duty here injoyn'd.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The perſons to whom the Precept is addreſs'd, were the <hi>Saints and faithful Brethren in Chriſt that were at Coloſs</hi> (for to them the Epiſtle is directed <hi>c.</hi> 1. <hi>v.</hi> 2.) That is, all the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans at <hi>Coloſs,</hi> of what order or quality ſoever. For theſe ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles <hi>(Saints and faithful Brethren)</hi> were not confined to any one order of Men, but vouchſafed in common to all Chriſtians.* Who were all call'd <hi>Saints,</hi> as they were by Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm ſeparated from the idolatrous World, and conſecrated to the ſervice of the true God: <hi>Brethren,</hi> as by Regenerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Adoption, they were all become the Sons of that one God and Father: <hi>Faithful,</hi> as they perſever'd in that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, notwithſtanding all Temptations to the contrary.</p>
            <p>It cannot therefore be queſtion'd, but that this Command was given to the Laity, as well as the Clergy; Yea to the Laity, rather than the Clergy; becauſe it doth not appear, that there were more than two Church-men at <hi>Coloſs,</hi> at the time when this Epiſtle was directed to them, namely, <hi>Archippus</hi> and <hi>Philemon;</hi> for <hi>Epaphras,</hi> by whom they had been firſt converted to the Chriſtian Faith, was now in bonds with S. <hi>Paul</hi> at <hi>Rome,</hi> Phil. 23.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:48914:3"/> 2. The Duty here enjoyn'd theſe Lay-Chriſtians is, That <hi>the word of Chriſt dwell in them richly, in all Wiſdom.</hi> Though by <hi>the word of Chriſt,</hi> is meant more eſpecially that word, which was at firſt ſpoken by Chriſt himſelf in perſon, and afterward confirm'd by his Apoſtles; yet it is not to be confin'd to that alone, but extended to that alſo, which was long before deliver'd by <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets. For ſince <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets, not only ſpake of Chriſt, but it was alſo the Spirit of Chriſt by which they ſpake, (as <note place="margin">1 Pet. 1. 11.</note> S. <hi>Peter</hi> expreſly tells us) the word ſpoken by them, was no leſs the <hi>word of Chriſt,</hi> than that which was preach'd by Chriſt himſelf. In brief, the whole divinely inſpired Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, is <hi>the word of Chriſt,</hi> both as he is the Author, and the principal ſcope and matter of it.</p>
            <p>Now what is the Duty theſe Lay-Chriſtians are exhorted to with reſpect to this <hi>word of Chriſt?</hi> Is it not to read it? Not to give it room ſo much as in their houſes? No, but to give it entertainment in their Hearts. To <hi>let it dwell in them,</hi> to let it dwell in them <hi>richly,</hi> to let it dwell in them richly, <hi>in all Wiſdom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. That it <hi>dwell in them.</hi> It is not ſaid, dwell <hi>with,</hi> but more emphatically dwell <hi>in</hi> them: Which denotes eſpecially, That they accuſtom themſelves to the attentive reading and ſtudy of it, till it become their Intimate and Familiar, be habitually preſent to their minds, as frequently and upon all occaſions in their thoughts, as a perſon is in the houſe in which he dwells. Though a Man may perhaps have but little converſe with thoſe who dwell in the ſame Houſe <hi>with</hi> him; yet he can be no more eſtrang'd from that which dwells <hi>in</hi> him, than he can from his own thoughts and inclinations.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Nor will it ſuffice, That it barely dwell in them, but it muſt dwell in them <hi>richly:</hi> which may have reſpect both to the word it ſelf, Let the <hi>word</hi> dwell richly; and to the ſubject in which it dwells, Let it dwell <hi>in you</hi> rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. 1. To the word it ſelf. It is not enough, that it dwell in them <hi>ſparingly,</hi> that they give entertainment to a paſſage
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:48914:3"/> here and there which beſt complyes with their own Humors; but they muſt entertain it indifferently, one part with an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other; The Commands muſt be received, with the like readineſs as the Promiſes; Nor muſt they think by admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting one Command, to compound with God for the rejecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of another; but thoſe Commands muſt be looked up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as worthy of all acceptation, which moſt directly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradict their moſt beloved luſts. 2. To the ſubject in which it dwells. It muſt not as a Sojourner be confined to a ſingle room, to ſome one power of the Soul (as it is in too ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, who give it entertainment in their underſtandings, but ſuffer it to have no place in their Wills and Affections) but it muſt be admitted into, and make its abode in every Faculty; in the Mind to enlighten it, in the Conſcience to awaken it, in the Will to bow it to an humble ſubmiſſion to the Divine Will. It muſt take poſſeſſion of the whole Man, like as Leven (to which the Goſpel is compared) diffuſes it ſelf thorough the whole lump. For</p>
            <p n="3">3. In both theſe reſpects it muſt dwell in them ſo plente<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, as to enrich them, not only with ſome one kind of Wiſdom, but with <hi>all Wiſdom.</hi> To bring them to the Knowledge, Belief and Practice of whatſoever is required to make them compleatly happy for ever. For that alone is accounted Wiſdom in the Scripture ſenſe, by which a Man is made <hi>wiſe to Salvation.</hi> All other Wiſdom in compariſon with this, being but a more creditable piece of Folly.</p>
            <p>From the words thus explained, many Doctrines are clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deducible. As.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That it is the Duty of Lay-Chriſtians to acquaint themſelves with the holy Scriptures: This is plain, becauſe they are here commanded to let the word of Chriſt dwell in them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That the holy Scriptures contain all things neceſſary to Salvation. This is alſo as evident. For where a Man may learn not only <hi>Wiſdom,</hi> but <hi>all Wiſdom,</hi> there can be nothing wanting that is neceſſary to Salvation.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:48914:4"/> 3. That all things neceſſary to Salvation, are ſo clearly contain'd in the holy Scriptures, that the common ſort of Chriſtians may attain to the underſtanding of them. For how can the word dwell in them <hi>in all Wiſdom,</hi> if any part of that Wiſdom which is neceſſary to Salvation, be ſo ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcurely expreſs'd, that they cannot underſtand the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of it?</p>
            <p>The firſt of theſe is that which I intend at preſent to inſiſt upon, <hi>viz. The obligation that lies upon Lay-Chriſtians, to acquaint themſelves with the holy Scriptures.</hi> This is the leaſt that can be hence inferr'd, ſince without this, the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures cannot be ſaid to <hi>dwell in them,</hi> much leſs to dwell in them <hi>richly,</hi> and <hi>in all Wiſdom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But though this is ſo plainly contain'd in the words, that nothing can be more; yet becauſe it is a Duty not only queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on'd by ſome, but expreſsly denied by others, I ſhall there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore confirm it by other ſuch arguments, as may be of force, not only to convince your Judgments of the Truth, but to engage your Wills to the Practice of it. As</p>
            <p n="1">1. Becauſe the holy Scriptures were by God himſelf at firſt directed and addreſs'd to Lay-men. That this Epiſtle to the <hi>Coloſſians</hi> was ſo, you have ſeen already. I ſhall now ſhew the ſame concerning other parts of holy Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture.</p>
            <p>The Moral Law was ſpoken by God to all the People, in ſuch an audible Voice, that they might all hear it. <hi>The Lord ſpake unto you out of the midſt of the fire,</hi> ſays <hi>Moſes,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Deut 4. 12, 13.</note> 
               <hi>Ye heard the voice of the words, and he declared unto you his Covenant.</hi> So clearly and plainly did God deliver this Law to them, that he is ſaid to <hi>talk with them face to face.</hi> The <note place="margin">Deut. 5. 4.</note> Statutes and the Judgments, that is, the Ordinances concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Ceremonial Worſhip, and the Laws about matters of Right between Man and Man, were not indeed ſpoken immediately to the People (no more were they to the Prieſts) but to <hi>Moſes</hi> himſelf, who by God's command recited them
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:48914:4"/> to the People, and wrote them in a Book, from which <note place="margin">Exod. 24. 3, 4. Deut. 31.</note> they might take a Copy of them.</p>
            <p>Nor were the Sermons of the <hi>Prophets</hi> committed to the <hi>Prieſts</hi> cuſtody, that according to their diſcretion the People might either more or leſs, or not at all be made ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with them; but they were by the Prophets ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs'd to the People themſelves. So God commanded them. <hi>Go and cry in the ears of Jeruſalem, ſtand in the gate</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Jer. 2. 2.</note> 
               <hi>of the Lord's houſe and proclaim theſe words, and ſay, Hear the word of the Lord all ye of Judah,</hi> &amp;c. And ſo the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets accordingly did. <hi>Hear the word of the Lord,</hi> ſaith <hi>Jere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Jer. 7. 2. Jer. 2. 4.</note> 
               <hi>O houſe of Jacob. Hear the word which the Lord hath ſpoken againſt you, O Children of Iſrael,</hi> ſaith the Prophet <hi>Amos, Hear the word of the Lord ye Kine of Baſham which</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Amos 3. 1. Amos 4. 1.</note> 
               <hi>are in the Mountain of Samaria.</hi> It is needleſs to inſiſt upon the proof of this, ſince nothing is more obvious, than that the Exhortations, Admonitions and Reproofs of the Prophets, were not only delivered in the audience of the People, but that thoſe of them in which the People were concern'd, were expreſsly directed to them. And therefore when <hi>Jeremy</hi> was ſhut up in the Dungeon, and could not ſpeak to the People himſelf, he commanded <hi>Baruch</hi> to write all the words of his Prophecy in a Book, and read them in the ears of all the People in <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and of all the people which came from the Cities of <hi>Judah</hi> to <note place="margin">Jer. 36. 8, 9.</note> 
               <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In like manner our bleſſed Saviour, though he ſpake as never Man ſpake, yet was he contented with the vulgar ſort of hearers. His firſt ſolemn Sermon was preached to his Diſciples; not to the twelve only, but to all thoſe who were deſirous to be inſtructed by him, out of which he choſe the twelve who were afterward call'd Apoſtles. But though his ſpeech was directed to his Diſciples, yet he ſo ſpake, as that the multitude alſo (who ſtood at a greater diſtance) might hear him; for S. <hi>Matthew</hi> expreſsly tells us, that the <note place="margin">Matth. 7. 28.</note> multitudes (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) were aſtoniſhed at his Doctrine. His
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:48914:5"/> Sermons at <hi>Capernaum, Nazareth,</hi> by the Sea ſide, and in the Wilderneſs, were they preached to Prieſts only? No, his Auditors for the moſt part were the rude and unlearned People. And can any Man reaſonably ſuppoſe, that he would not have thoſe Sermons read by Lay-men, which he thought fit to preach to ſuch?</p>
            <p>The Apoſtles of our Lord, not only preached to the common People, but ſent their Epiſtles alſo to them. The Epiſtles of S. <hi>Paul</hi> are for the moſt part directed to the <hi>Saints,</hi> to the <hi>faithful in Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> to the <hi>beloved;</hi> all which titles in thoſe days, were uſed in the ſame latitude, as the name <hi>Chriſtian</hi> is now with us. And that no Man may imagine they were to be confined to Chriſtians of a higher rank, they are expreſsly directed to <hi>all.</hi> So the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle to the <hi>Romans; To</hi> all <hi>that are at</hi> Rome <hi>beloved of</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rom. 1. 7.</note> 
               <hi>God,</hi> call'd to be Saints. The firſt Epiſtle to the <hi>Corin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians.</hi> To the Church of God at <hi>Corinth,</hi> to them that <note place="margin">1 Corinth. 1. 2.</note> are ſanctified in Chriſt Jeſus, called to be Saints, to <hi>all,</hi> that in every place call upon the name of Jeſus Chriſt our Lord. The ſecond Epiſtle. To the Church of God which is at <note place="margin">2 Cor. 1. 1.</note> 
               <hi>Corinth,</hi> with <hi>all</hi> the Saints which are in all <hi>Achaia.</hi> The E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle to the <hi>Philippians,</hi> to <hi>all</hi> the Saints which are at <hi>Philippi.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Philip. 1. 1.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The Epiſtles of S. <hi>James,</hi> S. <hi>Peter</hi> and S. <hi>Jude,</hi> were written to all the diſperſed Jewiſh Chriſtians. The firſt Epiſtle of S. <hi>John,</hi> to <hi>little Children, young Men,</hi> and <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers;</hi> that is, to Chriſtians of all ſizes and degrees. The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, To an <hi>elect Lady and her Children.</hi> The third, To a private Chriſtian. To conclude this argument; No Man can in reaſon ſuppoſe, but that thoſe perſons ſhould read their Epiſtles, to whom they wrote them: ſince therefore they wrote them to Lay-men, it cannot be imagined it was their intention, That Prieſts only ſhould read them.</p>
            <p n="2">II. Nor were the holy Scriptures only addreſſed to Lay-men, but (which is more) they alſo were plainly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to read, and acquaint themſelves familiarly with
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:48914:5"/> them. Thus God commanded the <hi>Jews,</hi> with reſpect to the Law given to them. <hi>The words which I command thee</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Deut. 6. 6, 7, 8.</note> 
               <hi>this day ſhall be in thine heart; and thou ſhalt teach them diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to thy Children, and ſhalt talk of them, when thou ſitteſt in thine houſe, and when thou walkeſt by the way, when thou lieſt down, and when thou riſeſt up; and thou ſhalt bind them for a ſign upon thine hand,</hi> &amp;c. What is the import of this Command, but that they ſhould familiarly converſe with the Divine Law? make it the matter of their daily meditation and diſcourſe; and that they ſhould not think it enough to acquaint <hi>themſelves</hi> with it, but ſhould take care to teach it to their <hi>Children,</hi> that the knowledge there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of might never fail, but deſcend from one generation to another. And to whom was this Command given? Not to the Prieſts and Levites only, but to the whole Body of the <hi>Iſraelites, Hear O Iſrael.</hi> The ſame in effect God af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward <note place="margin">Deut. 6. 4. Joſh. 1. 8.</note> commanded <hi>Joſhua. This Book of the Law ſhall not depart out of thy mouth, but thou ſhalt meditate therein day and night.</hi> It might not depart out of his mouth, he was therefore to read it and talk of it; and not only ſo, but to meditate therein day and night. Not that they were obliged in every moment of time to be thinking or ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Law of God, for that cannot be; and in caſe it could, it could not be a Duty, becauſe it would be incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent with other Commands: But that they were to take all fit occaſions, and beſides the more ſolemn ſeaſons, even in their worldly buſineſſes and Recreations, ſhould intermix ſome ſerious thoughts of it, to ſeaſon them withal: At leaſt, That they ſhould be often in this ſort of exerciſe, and never ſuffer any long ſpace of time to paſs wholly with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it.</p>
            <p>And to ſhew how highly God valu'd this Commandment, he promiſed the greateſt Reward to the diligent Obſervers of it. Of all the Promiſes of the Jewiſh Law, that of long life was the moſt deſirable; and therefore <hi>length of days,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Prov. 3. 16.</note> is placed by <hi>Solomon</hi> in the <hi>right hand of Wiſdom,</hi> as having
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:48914:6"/> the preeminence of <hi>Riches and Honour.</hi> And this God pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed the <hi>Jews,</hi> both for themſelves and their Children af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to quicken their obedience to this Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. <hi>Ye ſhall lay up theſe my words in your heart and</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Deut. 11. 18, 19, 20, 21.</note> 
               <hi>in your Soul, and bind them for a ſign upon your hand,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>That your days may be multiplied, and the days of your Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, in the land which the Lord ſware unto your Fathers, to give them, as the days of Heaven upon the Earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In ſucceeding times, the ſame Duty is inforc'd by <hi>David</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 1. 3. Pſal. 19. 7, 8, 9, 10, 11. Prov. 6. 22, 23. Prov. 8. 2, 3.</note> and <hi>Solomon,</hi> with great variety of powerful motives, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from the excellency of the Laws themſelves, and the ineſtimable benefits that do accrue to Men by the ſtudy and practice of them.</p>
            <p>And as God enjoyn'd this to the <hi>Jews,</hi> ſo in obedience to his Command, we find, That in the days of our bleſſed Saviour, the reading of the Scriptures was the common practice of that People. That queſtion he frequently put to them, <hi>have ye not read?</hi> plainly implies, that they had read the Scriptures. Yea, That Women were then ſo learned in the Scriptures, as to be able to inſtruct their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren therein, for S. <hi>Paul</hi> tells us, That <hi>Timothy</hi> had <hi>known the Holy</hi> Scriptures from a Child; which becauſe he could <note place="margin">2 Tim. 3. 16.</note> not learn from his Father, who was a Heathen; his ſo early inſtruction in the knowledge of them, was owing to his Grand-mother <hi>Lois,</hi> and his Mother <hi>Eunice,</hi> whoſe faith <note place="margin">2 Tim. 1. 5.</note> we find before commended.</p>
            <p>For the Scriptures of the new Teſtament. 1. As it is certain, That at the firſt writing of them, they were read by the People: For S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaking to ſuch, ſays, <hi>We write</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Corinth. 1. 13.</note> 
               <hi>none other things to you, than what you read.</hi> And again; <hi>When ye read,</hi> ſaith he to the <hi>Epheſians, Ye may underſtand</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Epheſ. 3. 4.</note> 
               <hi>my knowledge in the myſtery of Chriſt.</hi> And 2. As it is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, That the directing them to Laymen, was a virtual command to them to read them. So 3. No injunction can be more full to this purpoſe than that in the words of my Text. <hi>Let the word of Chriſt dwell in you richly in all</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:48914:6"/> 
               <hi>Wiſdom.</hi> Think it not enough, to give it entertainment now and then, as you do to a ſtranger, but let it dwell in you; and that not ſparingly, but ſo plentifully, that you may there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by abound in all Spiritual Wiſdom.</p>
            <p n="3">III. That the People are obliged to acquaint themſelves with the Holy Scriptures, will further appear, if we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the ſubject matter of them; That being ſuch as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns the People, as well as the Prieſts. Should the King put forth a Declaration of his Will and Pleaſure, which concern'd all States and orders of Men within his Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, would it not be the Duty of his Lay-Subjects, no leſs than of his Clergy, to enquire into it? the caſe is not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like in the matter now before us. Whether we conſider the Doctrines, the Precepts, the Promiſes, or the Threatnings contained in the Holy Scripture, we ſhall find that <hi>all</hi> Men (People and Prieſts, learned and unlearned) have a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon concern in them.</p>
            <p n="1">1. For the Doctrines. Every Man that is baptized hath obliged himſelf by Vow to believe all the Articles of the Chriſtian Faith: And every Man doubtleſs is concern'd in all thoſe Doctrines which he hath ſo ſolemnly Vowed to believe. Yea had he never made any ſuch Vow, yet all thoſe Doctrines, the belief of which is neceſſary to Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, he is as much concern'd to believe, as he is to be ſaved, and by neceſſary conſequence to acquaint himſelf with them; for can a Man believe that which he doth not know? Some Men, I know, tell us, that a Man may; That though he know not one Article of the Creed, yet if he believes, all that the Church believes, he may be ſaid to believe them all, becauſe the Church believes them. But if this be ſo, then a meer Heathen who never ſo much as heard of Chriſt, may be a right Catholick Believer; for ſince he believes in the groſs whatſoever God hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed, he may by the ſame way of believing, be ſaid to believe, That Jeſus is the only Son of God, that he was
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:48914:7"/> conceived by the Holy Ghoſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> becauſe theſe are ſuch Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles as God hath clearly revealed.</p>
            <p n="2">2. For the Commandments of God, Lay-men are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd to know them, becauſe they are concern'd to do them; they being no leſs the rule of their practice, than they are of Clergymens. Let it be ſhew'd, that any one Command of the Moral Law given by <hi>Moſes,</hi> did not extend to every <hi>Jew;</hi> Or that any one Command of the Chriſtian Law, deliver'd by our Saviour in his Sermon upon the Mount; does not oblige every Chriſtian, and we ſhall then grant, that thoſe perſons who are not bound to obey them, are no way oblig'd to make enquiry after them. The Clergy of the <hi>Church of Rome,</hi> in their Catechiſms for the uſe of the vulgar, have indeed commonly left out the Second Commandment; but the reaſon is, not becauſe they think the People are not concern'd to know it, but becauſe it highly concerns themſelves, to keep the People in ignorance of it, becauſe they have taught them to practiſe, ſo plainly contrary to it.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Promiſes can no leſs concern Lay-men, becauſe they were made on purpoſe to invite and encourage Men to yield obedience to the Commands; unleſs it may be ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, that the Laity are ſo forward of their own accord to do their duty, that they need no incitement; but the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy ſo backward and averſe, that they will not be brought to it without ſuch powerful Inducements.</p>
            <p n="4">4. For the threatnings of Divine vengeance in caſe of Diſobedience, it muſt be alſo granted, that the Laity are as much concern'd to know them, as the Clergy; if it be granted, that the Laity are as prone to break the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments of God, and as hardly reſtrain'd from ſin, as the Clergy are; which, I ſuppoſe, will not be denied, by thoſe perſons we now argue againſt.</p>
            <p>It is needleſs to proceed to other matters, ſince by what hath been already deliver'd it is manifeſt enough, That the things contain'd in Holy Scripture, are not appropriated to Church-men, but of ſuch univerſal concernment, that every
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:48914:7"/> perſon of what rank or quality ſoever, is obliged to ſearch into them.</p>
            <p n="4">IV. And for the Commandments eſpecially, let it be fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther conſider'd, That there are ſome Commands laid upon Lay-men, as well as others, which no Man can be capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of yielding obedience to, who is not converſant in the Holy Writings. I ſhall inſtance in three only. 1. To in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct their Children in the Scriptures. 2. To try the Spirits whether they be of God. 3. To give a reaſon of the hope that is in them.</p>
            <p n="1">1. To inſtruct their Children in the knowledge of the Scriptures. This God commanded the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> in the place frorecited. <hi>The words which I command thee this day ſhall be</hi> 
               <note place="margin">See alſo Deut. 4. 9. and chap. 32. 46.</note> 
               <hi>in thine heart, and thou ſhalt teach them diligently to thy Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren.</hi> Of the like import is S. <hi>Paul</hi>'s injunction to Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Parents, To <hi>bring, up their Children, in the nurture and admonition of the Lord.</hi> Hear what S. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> ſays upon theſe words. <hi>Wouldſt thou have thy Son obedient, nurſe him up from the beginning in the inſtruction and admonition of the Lord. Think it not more than needful, that he hear the Divine Scriptures; for there he will firſt hear this leſſon, Honour thy Father and thy Mother. Say not that this belongs to Monks; why doſt thou fear that which is greatly gainful? make him a Chriſtian. For it is moſt neceſſary for thoſe who converſe with the World, to know thoſe leſſons which are to be learnt from thence, eſpecially for Children.</hi> And a little after he adds. <hi>Let us make them from their childhood to apply them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the reading of the Scriptures.</hi> And can a Parent in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct his Children in the Scriptures, who does not ſtudy them himſelf?</p>
            <p n="2">2. To try the Spirits whether they be of God. This <note place="margin">1 Joh. 4. 1.</note> S. <hi>John</hi> commands, not only Biſhops and Prieſts, but all ſorts of Chriſtians to do. By <hi>Spirits</hi> are meant the Teachers who pretend to divine inſpiration; but now becauſe it cannot ordinarily be diſcerned, whether the Teachers are
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:48914:8"/> of God, but by the tryal of what they teach, they are there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore firſt to try the Doctrines, and as they find them either true or falſe, to conclude the Teacher either a true or a falſe Prophet.</p>
            <p>Now the Scriptures being the Rule by which Doctrines are to be tried, how can a Man make this tryal, who is not acquainted with them? Yea, ſhould we ſuppoſe, that the Scriptures are not the entire Rule (as the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent <hi>Church of Rome,</hi> in contradiction to the antient Church, and the Scriptures themſelves, teaches) but ſtand in need of unwritten Traditions to ſupply their defects: yet ſince the Romaniſts ſtill grant them to be the Rule, of all thoſe Doctrines they extend to; that whatſoever Doctrine is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver'd in them, is infallibly true; whatſoever is contrary to any Doctrine deliver'd in them, is certainly falſe; It plainly follows, that no Man can be qualified for the tryal of Doctrines, who is a ſtranger to them; becauſe no Man can know what Doctrines are either contrary or agreea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the Scriptures, before he knows, what are contain'd in them.</p>
            <p n="3">3. To give a reaſon of the Hope that is in them. <hi>Be</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. 3. 15.</note> 
               <hi>ready always,</hi> ſays S. <hi>Peter, to give an anſwer to every one that asketh you a reaſon of the hope that is in you.</hi> When your Religion is oppoſed and perſecuted, be ready not only to confeſs it, but to give a reaſon to every one that requires it, why you are Chriſtians. And what reaſon can a Man who knows not the Scriptures give, why he is a Chriſtian, rather than a <hi>Mahometan?</hi> unleſs the very ſame that a <hi>Turk</hi> can give, why he is a <hi>Mahometan,</hi> ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than a Chriſtian, <hi>viz.</hi> That he had the good fortune to be born and bred in a Nation, where the Chriſtian Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion was in faſhion.</p>
            <p>To conclude this argument: In that God commands thoſe things to be done by Lay-men, which no Man can do without the knowledge of the Scriptures, he alſo commands them to acquaint themſelves with the Scriptures; As he
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:48914:8"/> that requires the end, he alſo requires the uſe of thoſe means without which it cannot be obtained.</p>
            <p n="5">V. The uſes and ends to which the Holy Scriptures are by God deſigned, are a ſufficient proof of Lay-mens obligation to acquaint themſelves with them. 'Tis true, ſome parts of Scripture were intended for the uſe of Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and others of Hearers, conſider'd as ſuch on purpoſe to inſtruct them in thoſe Duties which belong to them, as ſo diſtinguiſhed the one from the other. But beſides thoſe Texts which are proper to them, with reſpect to their dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent ranks and ſtations; the uſes to which the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures are deſign'd, are ſuch which reſpect Men in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, both Laity and Clergy, of what degree or quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſoever.</p>
            <p>Such are in the general, To teach and inſtruct us in thoſe things by which we may be made wiſe to Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. S. <hi>Paul</hi> tells us, That <hi>whatſoever things were written</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rom. 15. 4.</note> 
               <hi>aforetime, were written for our learning.</hi> And if whatſoever was written by <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets, to thoſe who li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved before Chriſt came in the fleſh, to reveal the will of God more fully and clearly to us, was written not only for <hi>their</hi> learning, but for <hi>ours</hi> too; how much more what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever is written ſince by the Apoſtles and Evangeliſts? this being written for <hi>our</hi> learning only, and not for <hi>theirs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>More particularly</p>
            <p>They are deſign'd to teach us, what is neceſſary for us to know, and believe, and do that we may be ſaved. <hi>Theſe</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Joh. 20. 31.</note> 
               <hi>things are written,</hi> ſays S. <hi>John, that ye might believe that Jeſus is the Chriſt, the Son of God, and that believing, ye might have life through his name.</hi> And <hi>theſe things have I written</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Joh. 2. 1.</note> 
               <hi>to you, that ye ſin not.</hi> To this purpoſe they teach us not only our Duty in general; but what are thoſe ſins in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, that are to be avoided, and thoſe good works which God hath ordained that we ſhould walk in; and are admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably ſuted to the begetting and promoting of all thoſe hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:48914:9"/> virtues, by which we may be diſpoſed and enabled to deny all ſorts of ungodlineſs and worldly luſts, and to live ſoberly, righteouſly and godly in this preſent World; that having our fruit unto holineſs here, our end may be ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting life. In ſhort, the <hi>word of Chriſt,</hi> is the great inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which God hath ordained for the ſaving of Souls, and therefore it is call'd <hi>the Grace of God which bringeth Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation;</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Tit. 2. 11. Epheſ. 1. 13. Rom. 1. 24. Jam. 1. 21.</note> 
               <hi>the power of God to Salvation to every one that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieveth; the Goſpel of Salvation.</hi> And certainly no Man can deny that theſe uſes and ends of Holy Scriptures appertain to Lay-men, who does not place them in the order of Beaſts, and deny that they have Souls capable of immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Bliſs.</p>
            <p>Nor were they written to inſtruct the People as well as Prieſts in thoſe points only of Faith and Practice, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern them all in common as they are Men and Chriſtians; but more particularly yet, to teach Lay-perſons of both Sexes, of all Ages, Ranks and Relations, what Graces are moſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming, and how they ought to behave themſelves in that age, place or relation in which they are: That Men and Women, both Elder and Younger; Husbands and Wives, Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents and Children, Maſters and Servants, Magiſtrates and Subjects might there find what their reſpective Duties are, together with ſuch motives as may be of force to engage them to the doing of them. And can it reaſonably be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, when God hath ſo particularly preſcribed in his word, to all ſorts of Secular perſons their Duties, as they ſtand di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhed one from another, by their different ranks and relations, that it is his pleaſure they ſhould not look into it, to ſee what theſe Duties are?</p>
            <p>Furthermore, The Scriptures are deſign'd by God to teach Men, in all variety of fortunes, how to behave themſelves, and to improve their lot (whatſoever it be) to their beſt advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage. Be a Man poor or rich, high or low, in honour or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace, in ſickneſs or in health, he may learn from them, how to correct thoſe evils which are incident to that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:48914:9"/> in which he is, and to make it ſubſervient to his greateſt good. Yea, be a Man's condition never ſo ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamitous, though he <hi>walk in darkneſs and ſee no light,</hi> he may find in the <hi>word of Chriſt,</hi> thoſe inſtructions, directions, examples, precepts, promiſes, from which (if duly applyed) light will ariſe to him, in the midſt of his darkneſs. And therefore S. <hi>Chryſoſtom.</hi> in his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment on my Text, upon this account earneſtly exhorts the Men of the World to the ſtudy of the Scriptures. <hi>Hearken I beſeech you,</hi> ſays he, <hi>all ye who are employ'd in the affairs of this life; get ye Bibles, the Medicines of your Souls. If you will have no more, yet get at leaſt the New Teſtament, the Acts of the Apoſtles, the Goſpels, your conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual Teachers. If any grief happen to you, look into them, as the ſtorehouſe of Medicines, from thence fetch comfort in your ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamities,</hi> &amp;c. And good reaſon had he thus to exhort them. For can any Man in his wits imagine, that God would have that concealed from the Laity, which he in mercy de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign'd for the Remedy of all their ſpiritual Maladies? For</p>
            <p n="6">VI. (Which plainly follows from what has been deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd) Have not the Laity as much need of the Holy Scriptures, as the Clergy? Are they not liable to as many ſpiritual Infirmities and Diſeaſes, and therefore ſtand in as great need of Medicines to prevent or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move them? Are they ſo well acquainted with their Duty, that they cannot know it better? and in caſe they were, yet are they not as ſlow to good, and as prone to evil as other Men, and therefore need as much to be quicken'd to the practice of thoſe Duties they al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready know? Are they not expoſed to as violent aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaults of their Ghoſtly Enemies, as their Teachers are, and therefore need the Sword of the Spirit to repel them, as much as they? Yea, are they not more expoſed to Temptations from this evil World, than thoſe are, who
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:48914:10"/> live more retir'd from it, and have leſs to do with it? <hi>Say not,</hi> ſays <hi>Theophylact, that it belongs to the Religious</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Theoph</hi> in Epheſ. 6. 4.</note> 
               <hi>only to read the Scriptures, for it is the duty of every Chriſtian, eſpecially of thoſe who are converſant in the World, ſince they ſtand in need of greater help, as being in a ſtorm.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Beſides, ſince (as you have before ſeen) the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures are deſign'd to inſtruct Lay-perſons of all ſtates, ages and ranks, in their reſpective Duties; unleſs a ſort of Lay-men can be found, who are neither Young<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er nor Elder, Married nor Unmarried, Superiours nor Inferiours; who are neither in Sickneſs nor in Health, in Proſperity nor Adverſity, that is, ſuch a ſort of Lay-men, who are in no ſtate, condition or order of Men, none will be found who have not need of the Holy Scriptures.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> It will perhaps be ſaid, <hi>That it is not neceſſary to this, that they ſearch the Scriptures themſelves; It is ſufficient that they take them upon truſt from their Teachers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which I return theſe things.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. That our Saviour did not think this ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient; for he commanded Lay-men, as well as others not to take matters upon truſt, but to <hi>ſearch the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Joh. 5. 39.</note> Nor did S. <hi>Paul</hi> think it enough; for as he di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected his Epiſtles to <hi>all the Saints, to all that call up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 1. 13. Epheſ. 3. 4.</note> 
               <hi>the name of the Lord Jeſus,</hi> ſo he expected that <hi>all</hi> ſhould read them. And though he was guided by an infallible Spirit, yet S. <hi>Luke</hi> thought it a Virtue in the <hi>Bereans,</hi> and highly commends them for it, That <hi>they ſearched the Scriptures daily, whether thoſe things,</hi> which were <note place="margin">Act. 17. 11.</note> ſpoken by S. <hi>Paul, were ſo.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:48914:10"/>
            <p> 2. It may reaſonably be preſum'd, that thoſe Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers ſerve no good deſign, who forbid their People to ſearch the Scriptures. For what more likely reaſon can be given, than that they themſelves know that their Doctrines are ſuch, as will not abide the tryal? Would you not ſhrewdly ſuſpect that Man's Honeſty, who having gotten into his hands the Writings of another's Eſtate, in which he confeſſes you are highly intereſs'd, ſhall refuſe to let you ſee them, and confidently tell you, that you ought to know no more of them, than he ſhall think fit to acquaint you with? But.</p>
            <p>3. Suppoſing your Teachers deal honeſtly with you, it is but a ſmall portion of Scripture that they can ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint their People with, in compariſon of what they may read at home; Eſpecially the Teachers in the <hi>Church of Rome,</hi> where no more of the Scripture is commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated to thoſe, who do not underſtand the Latine Tongue, than what the Preacher is pleas'd to put into his Sermon, and that commonly is little enough. But in caſe the Scriptures were read in a Language the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple underſtood, yet from the tranſlent reading, they would carry away but little, and that little would ſoon be forgotten, unleſs kept in mind by reading and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation. And therefore S. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> frequently and earneſtly exhorted his People not to content themſelves with hearing the Scriptures, but to read them alſo pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vately at home; out of many I ſhall quote a paſſage or two to this purpoſe. <hi>I beſeech you to come to the Church</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hom.</hi> 29. <hi>in Geneſ.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>continually, and with diligence attend to the reading of the Divine Scriptures; and not only when you come hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but alſo at home to take the Divine Books into your hands, and carefully to receive the benefit of the things contain'd in them. Much profit does come from hence; firſt the Tongue by reading is reform'd, then the Soul is wing'd, and carried aloft,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Let us not I beſeech you care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſly</hi>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:48914:11"/> 
               <hi>neglect ſo great a gain, but alſo at home, let us with diligence apply our ſelves to the reading of the Divine Writings.</hi> And in another place, he thus addreſſes to his Hearers. <hi>Let every one, when he retires home, take</hi> 
               <note place="margin">De utilitate Lect. Scrip.</note> 
               <hi>the Bible into his hands, and run over the ſenſe of thoſe things that have been ſpoken, if he deſire to reap conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual and ſufficient benefit from the Scriptures: for bare hearing for two hours, is not ſufficient for our ſecurity.</hi> Theſe were the leſſons this Holy Man inculcated upon thoſe who daily attended to the publick preaching and reading of the word, and who heard the Scriptures read in a language they underſtood (which is not now permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the Roman Church) ſo neceſſary in his judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, was the private reading of the Scripture, that all that was heard in publick would not ſuffice without it. For it is not enough, that the word of Chriſt dwell in us ſparingly, but</p>
            <p>4. It muſt dwell in us richly, which it can never do, ſave in thoſe only who frequently read it, and medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate upon it. Some perſons I know there are who can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not read; ſome others who can, live in thoſe unhappy places where they cannot procure Bibles. If theſe do otherways, what in them lies to attain to the knowledge of the Scriptures, God will <hi>accept them according to that</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 8. 12.</note> 
               <hi>they have, and not according to that they have not:</hi> For unavoidable defects, he will either make allowances, or make a ſupply ſome other way. But for others who have both ability and opportunity of reading the <hi>word of Chriſt,</hi> as it is their bounden duty, ſo it can argue no leſs than contempt of God himſelf to neglect it. For ſince God hath condeſcended for their good to write it, how can they chuſe but entertain ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry low thoughts of him, who will not vouchſafe to read it?</p>
            <p n="7">
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:48914:11"/> VII. What has been ſaid of the need all Men ſtand in of the word of Chriſt, ſuggeſts another argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>viz.</hi> The great Evils they muſt needs lay themſelves open to who neglect the ſtudy of the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures. For by how much the leſs they know them, by ſo much the leſs muſt they know their duty; and by how much the more ignorant they are of their du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, by ſo much the leſs muſt they practiſe it. Yea, thoſe duties which they are plainly taught by the Law written in their hearts, they will be eaſily perſwaded to neglect: becauſe the great motives to quicken them to theſe, muſt be fetch'd from the Scriptures. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore no wonder, that many perſons ſo eagerly purſue the <hi>Pomps and Vanities of this wicked World, make pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion for the fleſh to fulfil the luſts thereof,</hi> and are <hi>led captive by the Devil at his pleaſure,</hi> who ſolemnly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced all theſe in their Baptiſm; becauſe for want of acquaintance with the Scriptures, they are deſtitute of thoſe forces, without which they cannot ſucceſsfully en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter theſe their ſpiritual enemies.</p>
            <p>Nor are ſuch perſons in more danger of falling into ſin in matters of Practice, than of being miſ-led in points of Belief; for having no ſolid foundation to bottom their Faith upon, thy will <hi>like Children be toſſed to and fro, and carried about with every wind of Doctrine, by the ſlight of Men, and cunning craftineſs whereby they lie in wait to deceive.</hi> It need not therefore ſeem ſtrange, if many perſons ſhould be ſeduc'd from that <hi>Faith which was once deliver'd to the Saints,</hi> and which they themſelves for ſome time made profeſſion of. In ſhort: <hi>Ignorance of the Scriptures,</hi> (as S. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> in his Comment upon my Text tells us) <hi>is the cauſe of all evil.</hi> How deplorable then muſt their condition be, who live in the conſtant diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſe and neglect of them?</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:48914:12"/>
            <p> Having already ſhew'd, That the things which are written were at firſt addreſs'd to Laymen; That God hath plainly commanded them to acquaint themſelves fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliarly with them; That the ſubject matter of the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scriptures, and the uſes and ends for which they were written, do concern the Laity; That ſome ſpecial Duties are laid upon them, which no Man can perform, who is not converſant in the Scriptures: Having alſo ſhew'd the great need the Laity ſtand in of them, the ineſtimable benefits they may receive by them, and the intolerable evils they will expoſe themſelves to in caſe they neglect the ſtudy of them:</p>
            <p n="8">VIII. What now remains to quicken you further to this great duty, unleſs it be to ſhew the vanity of thoſe objections which are made againſt it? It may indeed be juſt matter of wonder, to find any thing objected againſt a Duty ſo clear, and of ſuch great moment: Yet ſo it is, that ſome Men have dared to ſay thoſe things which (if they were true) might juſtly affright the People from it, and make them take it for a Sin, rather than a Duty, to read the Bible.</p>
            <p>In general it is ſaid, <hi>That the promiſcuous reading of the Scriptures by the vulgar, does more hurt than good.</hi> Becauſe in particular, it occaſions their falling into dangerous Errors both in matters of Faith, and in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Practice, ſo that if this liberty ſhould be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low'd, they will neither <hi>believe,</hi> nor <hi>live</hi> ſo as they ought: Which charge conſiſting of two parts, the one re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating to Belief, the other to Manners, that the anſwer may be the more clear and ſatisfactory, I ſhall conſider them diſtinctly and apart. And</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> Firſt, It is objected. <hi>That many peſtilent Sects and Hereſies which infeſt the Church, have taken their</hi>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:48914:12"/> 
               <hi>riſe from the reading of the Scriptures by Laymen; who for want of being qualified to underſtand them aright, do uſually wreſt them to a pernicious ſenſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What is commonly ſaid of the obſcurity of the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, may be conſidered elſewhere. At preſent I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn ſeveral things in anſwer to the objection as now propoſed, each of which ſingly conſidered would be a ſufficient anſwer.</p>
            <p n="1">1. This reflects foul diſhonour upon God himſelf. For what can be more highly derogatory both to his Wiſdom and Goodneſs, than to ſay, that he hath writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ſuch a Book for his People's uſe, which they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not read, but they will be in danger of being eternal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ruin'd by it. If this be ſo, they are then much be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holden to thoſe who take the Bible from them, but owe no thanks to God who gave it to them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Our bleſſed Saviour thought the ignorance of the Scriptures the cauſe of Hereſies, and the means he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribes to prevent and cure them, is the ſtudy of the Scriptures. <hi>Ye err,</hi> ſaid he to the <hi>Sadducees;</hi> what, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ye ſtudy the Scriptures? No, but <hi>becauſe ye know</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Matth. 22. 29.</note> 
               <hi>not the Scriptures.</hi> And though he very well knew, how maliciouſly the <hi>Jews</hi> were bent, to wreſt the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures to juſtifie their rejection of him; yet does he not reprove them for reading the Scriptures they ſo much abuſed, but contrariwiſe commands to read them again, and more diligently. <hi>Search the Scriptures, for they</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Joh. 5. 39.</note> 
               <hi>teſtifie of me.</hi> As if he had ſaid; You will not yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve on me, but take me for a Deceiver. I require you therefore not barely to read, but to ſearch the Scriptures (that is, attentively, throughly and imparti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally to read them) and you will then be convinced that I am indeed the Meſſiah, becauſe they ſo plainly teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie of me. This was the method our Saviour preſcribed, for the cure of that damnable Hereſie.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:48914:13"/>
            <p> Of the ſame judgment were his Apoſtles after him. S. <hi>Jude</hi> to fortifie his beloved Chriſtians againſt the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies of the Gnoſticks, commands them, to <hi>remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber the words which were ſpoken before by the Apoſtles of</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Jude v. 17.</note> 
               <hi>our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> The remembrance of the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, was (it ſeems) in his opinion the beſt Antidote againſt the Poiſon of thoſe Seducers; and this ſuppoſes their acquaintance with them, ſince no Man can re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member what he has no knowledge of. Yea, that very Text which is frequently produced to prove that by reading the Scriptures Men fall into Hereſies, is on the contrary a plain proof, that the not reading them ſo much as to become acquainted with them, is the true cauſe from whence this miſchief ariſes. For who were the Men that wreſted the Scriptures to their own deſtruction? One character of them is, that they were <hi>unlearned;</hi> unlearned in what? in the Holy Scriptures, (for in humane learning S. <hi>Peter</hi> himſelf was very un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learned.) And if want of learning in the Scriptures, be the cauſe of falling from the Faith, then doubtleſs the ſtudy of them, will be the beſt way to eſtabliſh Men in it. What? could S. <hi>Peter</hi> ſo much as dream, that the reading of this Epiſtle by thoſe Lay-Chriſtians to whom he wrote it, would be the way to corrupt their Faith, when he wrote it to them, on purpoſe to preſerve them ſound in it? ſo contrary was his judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to that of his pretended Succeſſour.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Suppoſing that the reading of the Scriptures hath been to ſome Laymen an occaſion of falling into damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Hereſies; does it thence follow, that they ought not to read them? This is as abſurd, as for a Man thus to argue: Some Men by eating have fallen mortally Sick, let no Man therefore for the future eat. Some Men have uſed their ſight to the chuſing of a wrong way, it is therefore every Man's duty to put out his
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:48914:13"/> eyes. The light of the Sun is by many Men abuſed to very ill purpoſes, the Sun therefore it ſelf ought to be extinguiſhed. And is it not an excellent Remedy, for a Man to ſtarve himſelf, that he may not fall ſick by eating? Or for a Man to make himſelf blind, leſt if he ſee, he ſhould chance to miſtake his way? 'Tis true, a Man may loſe his way, that has his eyes in his head; but is he ſure not to loſe it, by putting them out? So a Man by miſtaking the ſenſe of Scripture, may hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen to fall into Errors, but he that is altogether un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acquainted with it, lays himſelf open to all Deluſions, expoſes himſelf a prey to every Seducer.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The manifeſt truth is, that generally ſpeaking, not the Laity, but the Clergy, have been the Authors of Sects and Hereſies. The <hi>Novatian</hi> Sect ſprang from one Prieſt, the <hi>Donatiſt</hi> from two, (though it took its name from a Biſhop, who afterward eſpouſed it.) The <hi>Arian</hi> Hereſie from a Prieſt, the <hi>Pelagian</hi> from a Monk (the Provoſt of <hi>Ban<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or)</hi> The <hi>Neſtorian</hi> from a Biſhop and Prieſt, the <hi>Eutychian</hi> from a Prieſt, the <hi>Eunomian</hi> from a Biſhop, the <hi>Monothelite</hi> from ſeveral Biſhops joyntly. Even <hi>Bellarmine</hi> himſelf aſſerts, That <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bell. d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Rom. Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tif. l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 8. <hi>Quant<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> tametſi.</hi>
               </note> almoſt all the prime Authors of Hereſie, have been either Prieſts or Biſhops. And for thoſe Laymen, that have been Broachers of Hereſies, they have been (for the moſt part) not of the vulgar ſort, but Men of great parts and learning. Hereſie is indeed a work of the fleſh, but one too fine and ſubtile to be forged in a vulgar Brain, except ſuch Hereſies only as are very ſenſual, groſs, and brutiſh. It is S. <hi>Jerome</hi>'s obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Comment. in Oſ. c.</hi> 9.</note> That no Man can be the Founder of an Hereſie who is not a Man of great wit and parts. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore</p>
            <p n="5">5. If this way of reaſoning be admitted, the Clergy ſhould be forbidden to read the Scriptures, rather than
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:48914:14"/> the Laity; ſince they are the Men that have done the greateſt miſchiefs, by wreſting them to the broaching and maintaining of Sects and Hereſies. As there are ſome Church-men, who to ſhew their great reverence to the Scriptures, do uſually compare them to Knives and Swords, (becauſe a man may uſe them to bad, as well as good purpoſes), ſo there are others, who have made good theſe compariſons, by drawing ſuch Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines from them, by which the Church has been miſerably wounded, divided and rent into pieces. Should therefore the uſe of the Bible be denied to all thoſe Orders of Men, of which any perſons in thoſe Orders have been found to abuſe it; it muſt be denied to the Clergy too, and by conſequence to all Men. And then God may take his Book again to himſelf: Unleſs it pleaſe him to beſtow it upon ſome other ſort of Beings, (if any ſuch there are) that it is fitter for. And yet let it be conſider'd</p>
            <p n="6">6. That thoſe Hereſies which have been broached either by the Clergy or the Laity, are not chargeable upon the Holy Scriptures, any more than darkneſs up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Sun when the Earth is eclipſed. For as the darkneſs proceeds not from the Sun, (which is and ever will be the fountain of light) but from the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpoſition of the opacous Body of the Moon which intercepts its light; ſo the true cauſe of Hereſies is not the Scripture, but Mens inordinate Luſts and Paſſions, which interpoſe between them and the light of the glorious Goſpel of God, which would otherwiſe have ſhone into their hearts. Pride and Vain-glory, Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſs and Senſuality, or ſome other vice, are the proper fountains, from whence all thoſe Hereſies which create diſturbance to the Church are derived (as might be ſhew'd at large.) Such is the power of corrupt af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, that the Man who is ſway'd with them, can
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:48914:14"/> ſee nothing aright, how fairly ſoever repreſented; but will be as apt to wreſt the plaineſt as the moſt obſcure Texts, to his own deſtruction.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> It is objected ſecondly, <hi>That the reading of Scriptures is dangerous to the common People, becauſe thoſe things are recorded in them, which may occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their erring in Practice, as well as in Faith. For in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance,</hi> Noah<hi>'s Drunkenneſs,</hi> Lot<hi>'s Inceſt,</hi> Jacob<hi>'s fraud and lying in getting the bleſſing,</hi> David<hi>'s Murther and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dultery,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Which if expoſed to the view of the vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar, they may thereby be encouraged and provoked to the imitation of them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> It is ſtrange, that Men who own the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures for the word of the moſt holy God, <hi>who is of purer eyes than to behold evil,</hi> ſhould have the face to draw up this black charge againſt them.</p>
            <p>But were not theſe vicious examples to be found in the Scriptures in our Saviour's days? and yet as they were then freely read by the People, ſo the reading of them was ſo far from being reprehended, that it was approved by him. Were they not in the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures in the days of S. <hi>Paul?</hi> And yet he tells us, <hi>That all Scripture is profitable,</hi> not only for <hi>Doctrine</hi> and <hi>Reproof,</hi> but for <hi>Correction</hi> too, and <hi>Inſtruction in</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Tim. 3. 16.</note> 
               <hi>righteouſneſs.</hi> Yea do not the Scriptures themſelves frequently give this teſtimony of themſelves, That they are a Sovereign Preſervative againſt Vice, and that this was one great end to which God deſign'd them? E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven young Men, who are moſt obnoxious to the pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution of Sin, by attending to the Scriptures may cleanſe themſelves from it. For, <hi>wherewithal,</hi> ſays <hi>David, ſhall a young Man cleanſe his way? by taking</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 119. 9.</note> 
               <hi>heed thereto according to thy word.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:48914:15"/>
            <p> But ſuppoſe, theſe evil examples are of ſuch dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous conſequence, why are they ſo to the Laity only? Are all the Clergy of ſuch approved virtue, that a Temptation hath no power over them? This is an attainment above the Vulgar, which I preſume the <hi>Roman</hi> Clergy do not yet pretend to.</p>
            <p>But for a direct Anſwer to the objection, I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe theſe two things in the general. 1. That the Scripture it ſelf hath preſcribed a remedy againſt the evil of theſe Examples. 2. That the examples them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves are many ways advantageous to our good, for the prevention or cure of Sin, and for the promoting of Virtue in us.</p>
            <p>1. The Scripture it ſelf hath preſcribed a Reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy againſt the evil of theſe examples, and that ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral ways. 1. By furniſhing us with the moſt emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent examples of the contrary Virtues. 2. By for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidding thoſe very ſins under the ſevereſt penalties. 3. By telling us how ſeverely God hath puniſhed the ſins of many of thoſe good Men. 4. By ſetting be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore us many dreadful examples of God's judgment upon others for the like ſins.</p>
            <p n="1">1. By furniſhing us with the moſt eminent exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of the contrary virtues, which may be as power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful a motive to Good, as the other can be to Evil. If we impartially read the Scriptures, we ſhall find, that the vicious actions of good Men are but few, in compariſon of their vertuous actions there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded; and whatſoever the ſins be, that ſome of them were ſometimes overtaken with, we ſhall alſo find that not only others, but even they themſelves (for the moſt part) were at other times exemplary for the contrary Duties. I ſhall not ſtay to inſtance in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars. It may ſuffice, That the holy <hi>Jeſus</hi> is in Scripture ſet before us as ſuch an illuſtrious Pattern,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:48914:15"/> not only of this or that, but of all kinds of Moral Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, as will to every attentive conſidering perſon, be of greater force to excite to virtue, than the ſins of all good Men there regiſtred, taken together, can be to provoke to the contrary.</p>
            <p n="2">2. By forbidding thoſe very ſins under the ſevereſt pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalties. What though in telling the Story of the evil actions of good Men, it does not always paſs a cenſure upon them? It was not needful it ſhould do ſo, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe God hath expreſly condemn'd them by his Law. It is the Law of God that is our only Rule. Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples therefore are to be judg'd by Precepts, and all Examples to be concluded bad, ſo far as they do not agree with the Rule.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Scriptures alſo tell us, how ſeverely God has puniſhed the ſins of many of thoſe good Men. He will have no encouragement to imitate <hi>David</hi> in his Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and Adultery, who conſiders that diſmal train of puniſhments that follow'd at the heels of them. For though God upon his Repentance forgave the eternal puniſhment, yet he viſited his iniquity with rods, and his ſin with ſcourges; he puniſhed him even to exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in this World, to the end, that others might ſee and fear, and do no more ſo preſumptuouſly. Nor can that Man be encouraged to fraud and lying by <hi>Jacob's</hi> exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in getting the bleſſing, who duly conſiders, how very dear thoſe ſins afterward coſt him.</p>
            <p n="4">4. We find in Scripture many dreadful examples of God's Judgments upon others for the like ſins, on purpoſe to deter us from them. S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſays thus of the Plagues God brought upon the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> in the Wilderneſs. <hi>Theſe things were our examples, to the intent that we ſhould</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Corinth. 10. 7, 8, 9, 19.</note> 
               <hi>not luſt after evil things, as they alſo luſted: neither be ye Idolaters as were ſome of them; neither let us com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit Fornication as ſome of them committed, and fell in one</hi>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:48914:16"/> 
               <hi>day three and twenty Thouſand; Neither let us tempt Chriſt as ſome of them tempted, and were deſtroyed of Serpents; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther murmur as ſome of them alſo murmured, and were deſtroyed of the Deſtroyer. Now all theſe things happen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to them for enſamples, and they are written for our admonition, upon whom the ends of the World are come.</hi> Let Men but carefully read, and ſeriouſly lay to heart theſe, and other ſuch terrible examples we find in Scripture, of God's vengeance upon Men for their ſins, and this doubtleſs will be a powerful Antidote againſt the infection of bad Example. Thus you ſee that what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever ill uſe ſome Men may be enclin'd to make of the ſins of good Men recorded in Scripture, the Scripture it ſelf hath provided a ſufficient Remedy againſt it. But this is not all:</p>
            <p>2. The ſins of good Men recorded in Scripture may be highly beneficial to us, both for the preſerving us from ſin, and the promoting of Holineſs in us, And that ſeveral ways.</p>
            <p n="1">1. As they are a confirmation of the truth of the Sacred Hiſtory, and by conſequence more fully aſſure us, that thoſe dreadful puniſhments there recorded as inflicted by God upon ſinners, are not cunningly devi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed fables, but the moſt indubitable Truths. For can we think, that the Penmen of theſe Books were not Men of the greateſt ſincerity, ſuch as would report nothing but what they knew to be true, when we find, that they did not conceal thoſe things, that were moſt diſgraceful to themſelves? Thus <hi>Moſes</hi> relates his own <note place="margin">Exod. 4. 10, 13, 14, 24, 25.</note> Faults, <hi>viz.</hi> his neglect to circumciſe his Son, his great backwardneſs to go upon that errand upon which God ſent him, his not ſanctifying the name of God at <note place="margin">Numb. 20. 12, 13.</note> the Waters of <hi>Meribah,</hi> and how the anger of God was kindled againſt him for theſe ſins. <hi>David</hi> hath left a memorial to all Poſterity of ſuch enormous ſins com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:48914:16"/> by himſelf, which the more ingenuous ſort of <note place="margin">Pſal. 51.</note> Heathens abhorr'd the very thoughts of. S. <hi>Peter</hi> hath given a more particular account than any of the other Evangeliſts, of his own denial and abjuration of his Maſter, in the Goſpel written by S. <hi>Mark;</hi> (for that Goſpel was dictated by S. <hi>Peter,</hi> S. <hi>Mark</hi> was only the <hi>Amanuenſis).</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. As they ſerve to beat down ſpiritual Pride, and to make us more humble, by repreſenting to us our own vileneſs, in the foul ſins of others who were better than our ſelves. And by how much the more humble, by ſo much the more holy we are; Humility being not only a Grace it ſelf, but the Parent and Nurſe of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other excellent Graces.</p>
            <p n="3">3. As they quicken us to greater watchfulneſs againſt ſin, make us more careful to avoid all occaſions, and to repreſs the very firſt motions toward evil. This uſe the Apoſtle teaches us: for having ſhew'd how ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> ſinn'd, and how remarkably they were puniſh'd, he concludes, <hi>Wherefore let him that thinketh</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Corinth. 10. 12.</note> 
               <hi>he ſtandeth take heed leſt he fall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. As they teach us to lift up our eyes and our hearts unto God, from whom alone cometh our help; to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plore continually the aſſiſtance of his Holy Spirit, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able us to ſubdue our evil inclinations, to withſtand all the Temptations of the World, the Fleſh and the Devil, and by patient continuance in well doing to ſeek for glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and honour and immortality.</p>
            <p n="5">5. As they teach us Thankfulneſs to God for his preventing and aſſiſting Grace, in caſe we have with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood thoſe Temptations, which other good Men have been overcome by, and preſerv'd from thoſe ſins into which they have fallen: ſince it is not by any ſtrength originally in our ſelves, but by the Grace of God, that we ſtand. And by how much the more thankful any
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:48914:17"/> Man is for the Grace he hath already received, by ſo much the more he may expect.</p>
            <p n="6">6. As they teach us to be charitable in our Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of others, and not preſently to conclude a Man loſt, though he fall into ſome great ſin, but en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to reſtore him again with the ſpirit of meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. But</p>
            <p n="7">7. If through our neglect and careleſneſs we fall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to any great ſin, we are by theſe examples encourag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to riſe again. What greater encouragement to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance than the hope of a pardon in caſe we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent? And this we can have no reaſon to deſpair of, when we find that others who fell into as foul ſins, were actually pardon'd, and received into God's favour upon their Repentance. Thus we ſee how thoſe evil examples we meet with in the holy Scripture, may be highly advantagious to our ſpiritual Good.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="application">
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:48914:17"/>
            <head>THE APPLICATION.</head>
            <p n="1">1. FRom what hath been ſaid it plainly follows, That thoſe Teachers who withhold the Scriptures from the Vulgar, have not that regard they ought to have, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to the Commandments of God, or to the good of their People. How careful thoſe of the <hi>Church of Rome</hi> are to keep the People from being acquainted with them, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by hearing them in publick, or by reading them in private is well known.</p>
            <p>It is true, that Leſſons out of the Scriptures, and Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles and Goſpels, are read in their publick Service, but how are they read? In a language that the Vulgar do not underſtand; that is ſo, as that they know as little of them after they are read, as they did before; As the dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs is as great when a Candle is in the houſe, as when there is none, if that Candle be hid under a Buſhel.</p>
            <p>But if they give the People ſo little of the Bible in publick, do they not make ſome amends for this, by allowing them the free uſe of it in private? I anſwer, No. No Man is allow'd to read, or ſo much as to have <note place="margin">Rule <hi>4th</hi> of the <hi>Index Expurg.</hi> made by order of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil of <hi>Trent.</hi>
               </note> the Bible in the Vulgar tongue (though tranſlated by thoſe of their own Church) without a Licence from the Biſhop of the Dioceſs, or the Inquiſitor, with the advice of the Pariſh Prieſt or Confeſſor; which Licence they muſt have in writing. And if any Man ſhall preſume without ſuch Licence either to read or have it, he may not receive Abſolution of his ſins, unleſs he firſt deliver up his Bible to his Ordinary. This is the ſtanding Law
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:48914:18"/> of the <hi>Church of Rome,</hi> eſtabliſh'd by the authority of the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> and confirm'd not only by Pope <hi>Pius</hi> IV. but by many ſucceeding Popes; which, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I have heard confidently denyed, by ſome of their ignorant Proſelytes, I will therefore refer them to a late Author in their own language (to whom I preſume they will give credit) who in his Chapter of reading the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scriptures, gives this Character of a Papiſt. <hi>It is</hi> 
               <note place="margin">A Papiſt Miſrepre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented and Repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> c. 10.</note> 
               <hi>true he does not think it (viz.</hi> the Holy Scripture) <hi>fit to be read generally by all without a Licence, or in the vulgar Tongue.</hi> And having told you why he does not think ſo, he adds: <hi>For theſe reaſons he is taught, that it is not convenient for the Scripture to be read indifferntly by all Men, but only by ſuch as have expreſs Licence, and good teſtimony from their Curates,</hi> &amp;c. And is not this courſe as effectual, to keep the generality of the Laity from reading the Scripture, as the abſolute forbidding it would have been? For how few will be at the trouble and charge of procuring a Faculty, when it cannot be had but from the Biſhop or Inquiſitor? Or if many were willing to be at the pains and coſt, yet few of thoſe many will be able to obtain it: For how few will be able to ſatisfie the Biſhop or Curate, that they are ſuch as will receive no hurt by reading, when they cannot ſo much as ask it without being ſuſpected of Hereſie? So that all things conſider'd, it may reaſonably be preſumed, that the effect of ſuch Licences will amount to little or nothing. And yet how little ſoever it be, it was thought too much to be granted: For by the Order of Pope <hi>Clement</hi> VIII. this obſervation is added to the Rule: <hi>That hitherto by the Command and practice of the holy Roman and univerſal In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſition, the Faculty of granting ſuch Licences for reading or keeping Bibles in the vulgar Tongue, or any ſummaries or hiſtorieal compendiums of the ſaid Bibles, is taken away, which is to be inviolably obſerved.</hi> And if no ſuch Licence
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:48914:18"/> can be legally granted, then no Man of what quality ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever can read the Scripture in the vulgar Tongue, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out tranſgreſſing the Laws of the Roman Church.</p>
            <p>I am not ignorant, that in this Kingdom, and I ſuppoſe, in ſome others, where the Reformation hath got conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable footing, ſome Lay-perſons of that Communion, are permitted to have the Bible in their own Tongue. But this permiſſion is directly contrary to their Laws, and extorted from them in theſe Countries to prevent a greater miſchief which they ſee would otherwiſe enſue; If you make en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry in <hi>Spain</hi> or <hi>Italy,</hi> you will find no ſuch indulgence there. I ſhall add only this. That in the Index of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited Books publiſhed by Pope <hi>Alexander</hi> VII. not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thoſe Bibles that are tranſlated and printed by Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks, but all Bibles in any vulgar Tongue are abſolutely prohibited.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Let us then be thankful to God, and bleſs and praiſe, and ſpeak good of his name, for that we have been born and brought up in a Church, which allows free liberty of ſearching the Holy Scriptures; and not only ſo, but lays it as a Duty upon all Men, and endeavours to quicken them thereunto by the moſt powerful motives. How earneſt our Church is in preſſing this Duty upon her Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, you may ſee in her <hi>exhortation to the reading of the holy Scriptures,</hi> a ſmall part of which I ſhall tranſcribe, deſiring you at your leiſure attentively to read the whole. Thus then ſhe beſpeaks us: <hi>If we profels Chriſt, why are we not aſham'd to be ignorant of his Doctrine? See<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that every Man is aſhamed to be ignorant in that learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing which he profeſſeth. That Man is aſham'd to be call'd a Philoſopher, which readeth not the Books of Philoſophy; and to be call'd a Lawyer, an Aſtronomer or Phyſician, that is ignorant in the Books of Law, Aſtronomy and Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick. How can any Man then ſay, that he profeſſeth Chriſt and his Religion, if he will not apply himſelf (as</hi>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:48914:19"/> 
               <hi>far forth as he can or may conveniently) to read and hear, and ſo to know the Books of Chriſt's Goſpel and Doctrine? Although other Sciences be good and to be learned, yet no Man can deny, but this is the chief, and paſſeth all other incomparably. What excuſe ſhall we therefore make (at the laſt day before Chriſt) that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light to hear or read Mens phantaſies and inventions, more than his moſt Holy Goſpel? and will find no time to do that, which chiefly (above all things) we ſhould do? and will rather read other things than that, for the which we ought rather to leave reading of all other things. Let us therefore apply our ſelves, as far as we can have time and leiſure, to know God's word, by diligent hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and reading thereof, as many as profeſs God, and have faith and truſt in him.</hi> And having ſhew'd the vanity of thoſe excuſes, which are commonly made by thoſe who have no good affection for the Scripture, ſhe concludes, <hi>Surely none be Enemies to the reading of God's word, but ſuch as are either ſo ignorant, that they know not how wholſome a thing it is; or elſe be ſo ſick, that they hate the moſt comfortable Medicine that ſhould heal them; or ſo ungodly, that they would wiſh the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſtill to continue in blindneſs and ignorance of God.</hi> Whereupon ſhe earneſtly renews her Exhortation, in theſe words. <hi>Let us thank God heartily, for this his great and ſpecial gift, beneficial favour, and fatherly providence. Let us be glad to receive this ſpecial gift of our Heavenly Father. Let us hear, read and know theſe Holy Rules, Injunctions and Statutes of our Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion. Let us with fear and reverence lay up in the Cheſt of our Hearts theſe neceſſary and fruitful Leſſons. Let us night and day muſe, and have meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and contemplation in them,</hi> &amp;c. And yet as if ſhe thought not this enough, <hi>in the Information for them which take offence at certain places of the Holy Scripture,</hi>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:48914:19"/> ſhe renews the Exhortation again, and preſſes it with variety of cogent Arguments.</p>
            <p>So far is the <hi>Church of England</hi> from declining the Holy Scriptures, that ſhe thinks ſhe can never too ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemently preſs her Children to ſearch into them. She knows her Doctrines will abide the Trial, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore deſires they may be expoſed to the open light, being confident, that the more they are examined, the more they will be approved. As ſhe hath taken no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing from the Scriptures, ſo neither hath ſhe added any new Doctrines contrary to them, and therefore need not conceal any part of them in an unknown tongue.</p>
            <p n="3">3. How great then is their Sin, who while they own themſelves members of this Church, do ſeldom take the word of God into their hands, much leſs lay it up in their Hearts; make it no part of their medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and ſtudy. God will not impute to their condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation the not reading of the Bible, whoſe lot is fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len in thoſe unhappy places where they can by no means procure it. But for us, who have not only free liberty to read it, but are ſo earneſtly preſſed by our Church to make it the matter of our ſtudy; if we uſe it no more, than thoſe who are forbidden the uſe of it, what Apology can we make for our ſelves? Our ſin, alas! is wilful, and utterly inexcuſable; a plain contempt of God, and our Duty, and therefore our puniſhment will be more grievous and intolerable. This will be our Condemnation, that light is riſen to us, but we ſhut our eyes, and will not ſuffer it to ſhine into our hearts, becauſe our deeds are evil; <hi>for</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Joh. 3. 19. 20.</note> 
               <hi>every one that doth evil hateth the light, neither cometh he to the light, leſt his deeds ſhould be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:48914:20"/> 4. Be then exhorted to apply your ſelves to the ſtudy of the Holy Scriptures; let us take all opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of hearing them when read and preached in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick; and not only ſo, but of acquainting our ſelves more familiarly with them in private: let us with <hi>David</hi> make them our daily Companions, our delight and our Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellors.</p>
            <p>If either the love of God or of our ſelves; If the conſideration of our Duty or of our Intereſt, of our preſent or future good will ſway with us, we ſhall need no other Motives, than thoſe arguments already propoſed, which I therefore beſeech you ſeriouſly to reflect upon.</p>
            <p>Many I know pretend, that they have ſo much o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther buſineſs, that they can find no leiſure to look into the Scriptures. I deſire thoſe perſons who make this Plea, to conſider theſe few things:</p>
            <p n="1">1. Have you any buſineſs of greater concernment than this? Can any thing be of greater moment than to know wherein your true happineſs conſiſts, and what conditions are required of you in order to the attainment of it? Can any thing be more neceſſary, than to be acquainted with your Duty, and with thoſe powerful Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives that may prevail with you to practiſe it? Is not this the <hi>one</hi> thing neceſſary? So our Saviour thought. <hi>Martha,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Luke 10. 41, 42.</note> 
               <hi>Martha,</hi> ſays he, <hi>thou art careful and troubled about ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny things but there is one thing needful, and Mary hath choſen the better part.</hi> And what was that one thing need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful that <hi>Mary</hi> had choſen, but to ſit at Chriſt's Feet and hear his word, that ſhe might do it?</p>
            <p n="2">2. You who pretend you have no leiſure for reading the Scriptures, do not many of you find time enough for worthleſs impertinent matters? if not alſo for ſuch as are hurtful? Do you not ſpend hour after hour in light and trifling diſcourſe? Have you not time for Feaſts, and merry mettings, for Cards and
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:48914:20"/> Dice, for Taverns and Play-Houſes? How many morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hours (more than need) do many perſons ſpend in their Beds, or in attiring themſelves when they get up? Who cannot find one hour to ſpare for ſtudying the will of God. And are theſe matters of ſuch great concernment?</p>
            <p n="3">3. Many of you who ſeem to ſpend your time to bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter purpoſes, what are the great buſineſſes you lay it out upon? What? but to heap up riches, and to raiſe your fortunes in the World? And are theſe mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of ſuch weight, that they deſerve to be put in the ballance againſt your everlaſting concernments? Is it more neceſſary to leave a rich Heir behind you, than to enrich your Souls with the treaſures of Divine Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and Grace? when God ſhall call you to your great Accounts, will he, think you, take this for a good Plea? Lord my time was all little enough for the get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of ſuch an Eſtate, and therefore I pray thee have me excuſed for neglecting to ſtudy thy Word.</p>
            <p n="4">4. You who can find no time for enquiring into the word of God, conſider ſeriouſly, That you muſt ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly find a time to die in. When death comes, it will not be put off to a more convenient ſeaſon; but will force you, whether you will or no, to be at leiſure; and will effectually convince you, that you had time enough, had you but had hearts to uſe it, for ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainting your ſelves with the Holy Scriptures. For if you be not then quite beſotted (as many perſons are, by the long courſe of a ſenſual worldly life, and by God's juſt judgment upon them) theſe and ſuch like, will be your ſad reſentments. I am now going to make my appearance before the great and righteous Judge of all the World, and what ſhall I ſay, who have had ſo little reſpect to his Word by which I muſt be judged, that I have not vouchſafed to read it?
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:48914:21"/> Can I ſay, that I had not leiſure? I cannot be ſo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudent, when I found time not only for a thouſand im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinent trifles, but for my Vices. O that I had ſpent that time in devout meditation on the Law of God, that I miſ-ſpent in ſenſual Pleaſure, or in heaping up of Riches! O that that time had been laid out in beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifying and adorning my Soul with Divine Grace, that was laid out in enquiring after Faſhions, in getting fine Cloaths, and in dreſſing my Body <hi>A la mode!</hi> But woe and alas! theſe wiſhes are vain, and to no purpoſe; It is now too late, the time is paſt, and will never return again. Conſider therefore</p>
            <p n="5">5. That the true reaſon why you do not find time to read the Bible, is not want of leiſure, but want of inclination and affection to it. You can find nothing there, that ſutes with your carnal and worldly Appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tites. The thoughts of God, and of the things of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other World, are ſuch as you can take no pleaſure in, and the groſs and ſenſual entertainments of this World, are the only things you have a reliſh for. But then conſider withal, that unleſs the temper of your Souls be changed before you die, unleſs you become new Creatures, and get a taſte and reliſh for the things a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove, you are not ſo much as capable of entering in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Kingdom of Heaven.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:48914:21"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
